- Hey folks, and welcome
to the introductory lesson
to the Fundamentals
unit of Learn UI Design.
This unit is all about the
fundamentals of design,
and I wanna kind of set it apart
from maybe other curricula
that you have seen about
the fundamentals of design,
because many lessons
that go into detail about
what they consider the
fundamentals of design
are just awfully useless,
and they cover things
like gestalt or balance,
or ideas like this that to
me are just not practical.
Even as a beginning designer,
I could read for hours about
gestalt or balance, but those
things just didn't help me
make my bad designs better.
And instead, what I wanna focus on is
the fundamentals of design that helped me,
and not just in one design or a couple,
but in every design,
no matter the context,
no matter the platform
you're building for,
no matter the brand
that you're working on.
Things like alignment,
spacing, consistency,
these are things that
come up again and again.
Even when you break the kind
of, quote, unquote, "rules"
that we're talking about in this unit,
you will know why you broke them,
and you will have first become
a master of following them.
So let's get started.
Throughout a lot of this unit,
I'm going to be teaching what
you could consider heuristics.
A heuristic just means
it's a rule of thumb.
It's sort of a go-to idea
that maybe doesn't apply
100% of the time, but
it's sure gonna point you
in the right direction a lot of the time.
And the reason heuristics are useful is
because they can take a space
of a lot of different possibilities
and choices and options,
and really quickly limit
it down to a manageable few
that you can try out.
And so, I wanna start by making a point
that aesthetics is not magic.
There's nothing magical to it.
It is a skill, but it's a skill
that you can get better at.
And in this course, I
try and encourage you
to get better at it through analysis,
analyzing good designs and why they work,
and analyzing bad designs
and why they don't work.
To me, when someone says
design is subjective,
what that tells me is
they haven't actually
analyzed it enough, because
a design is something that
has to serve a purpose.
It has a goal in mind.
It's not art.
Art, you hang on a wall.
Art, you might hang on your fridge,
but design you're not gonna do that with.
Design has to serve some purpose.
If I'm making a portfolio,
I want people to hire me,
and the design of my
portfolio can be judged
by a couple of criteria.
Does it get people to hire me?
Does it give some sense of who I am,
and set me apart from
other designers, et cetera?
So I don't think design is magic.
I don't think design is subjective,
but I would say design is open-ended,
and that is one of the big
things that people mean
when they say it's
subjective, or a it's magical,
or it's difficult, or
mysterious, or whatever.
It's open-ended because
even in the simplest case
there is a staggering number of choices
that you could choose
from in what you want
to end up with as your design.
So here, you know, I have this,
quote, unquote, "portfolio."
It's really just two pieces of text,
a headline and then a short
piece of text below it.
But in laying these two
elements out on the page,
I have so many options to choose from.
I mean, first of all,
there's the choice of what font to use.
So I have this Roboto, size 32,
but this size could, I mean,
it could be basically anything, right?
We talk about failing
left and failing right,
and that gives us an
enormous number of choices
of what to use as a font size.
Likewise, the font itself,
so even in just picking as
something as simple as a font,
there's hundreds of choices.
Multiply that by the number of,
quote, unquote, "acceptable font sizes,"
and you're already at
thousands of choices.
And even with some of the
text styling choices you make,
uppercase versus not uppercase,
that just doubles the number
of choices to choose from.
And then there's font weight.
I can choose 100, 300, 500, 700.
Even headlines, I could make them italics.
That's not out of the question.
So just in styling one piece of text,
there's something like a
quarter million options
that I am choosing from just to get here,
and then multiply that
by all of the options
for this second piece of text down here,
and then add in the decisions
you need to make about positioning.
How long are these lines gonna be
before they run over to the next line?
What's the top margin on this
piece of text right here?
What's the space in between them?
What's the space in between lines of text,
and in between paragraphs
of text, et cetera?
It goes on and on.
Someone else could do the math on this.
But my point is when you have
two pieces of text on a page
and you design them in one particular way,
you are picking out one
way out of like trillions.
The only way to deal with a decision space
that is that large, and this
applies to other disciplines
besides design, but if you have
trillions of possibilities,
how do you narrow those down?
One of the very best ways is
to have rules of thumb or heuristics.
That's why we're gonna be covering these,
and then another thing is
to know what not to do,
because that's just gonna
automatically eliminate
so many possibilities, right?
If you have the constraint
that, for instance,
your header should not be
smaller than your body text,
already that just takes
out so many possibilities
from those trillions.
And so, by knowing what not to do,
and also having some
helpful rules of thumb
of what positive options
I could check out,
that's gonna do a lot of the heavy lifting
and to letting us just spend our time
exploring good options,
rather than getting bogged down
in the myriad of bad possibilities.
Now, the structure of
this unit is such that
it's organized into an overarching system.
Each of the videos are not
necessarily just standalone ideas
that kind of exist in a vacuum,
but instead it sort of builds up,
and ultimately will
give you six core tools
that you're gonna use on
basically every design
that you ever do.
And I say, basically, I actually
think it is every design
that you ever do, but I'll
just hedge my bets here,
and I'll say it's basically
in every single design.
And this is unusual,
because, for instance,
it's not true of the color unit,
or the typography unit.
In the color unit, we'll talk
about some color palette ideas
that say only really work
if you're trying to make
a quirky-looking, artistic kind of design,
or in the topography unit I
might recommend some fonts
that basically only make sense to use
if you really want this
sort of strong, techie,
kind of sci-fi vibe from your site.
But in this unit, the
ideas that I talk about
apply basically everywhere,
and they build on top of each other
to create a toolkit of six tools
that you will use to make
a messy design look clean.
And this idea of making
a messy design look clean
might seem kind of like a niche thing.
It just might be one task
among many that you do.
But in my opinion, it's
actually fundamental
to being a good designer.
The task of making a messy
design look clean happens
far often than you might expect,
and the reason why is because many things
fall under the category of messy design.
For instance, let's say you
do a sketch of a screen.
You're working on a project with a friend,
and you sketch out some screens.
You kind of know what buttons
and interface elements
you wanna put on it,
but that sketch is messy.
It doesn't look great.
Well, that sketch is a messy design
that you want to make look clean.
Likewise, maybe you're doing some work
for a new client and they
took a stab at things
and went ahead and developed an app,
and it doesn't look very pretty,
but it gets the job done.
That's a messy design that you are going
to be hired to help make simple and clean.
Or say, for instance, that you're working
with some UX designers
who create wireframes.
A wireframe is
intentionally not gonna look
super, super nice.
It's just gonna be kind of
this low fidelity version
of the design.
It has the elements you need to include,
but it doesn't look great.
So in all of those cases, you
have this fundamental problem
of making a messy design looks simple,
and that's what the system
in this unit is for.
So the biggest question here is
what are those six core tools?
Well, you could look
ahead at the lesson names,
and figure out a couple of them.
The first three have their
own lessons dedicated to them,
alignment, spacing, and consistency.
These are the most involved topics,
and in each of these strategies,
you're going to have a
number of sub-heuristics,
and kind of ideas that apply
underneath these umbrellas.
The second three videos I actually combine
into one video in the Simplicity video,
which kind of covers
the system as a whole.
Lightening, hiding, and removing are
the three key strategies
for removing emphasis
from elements on the page.
And as you can imagine, these
are somewhat simpler topics,
but worth calling out
as individual strategies
in this toolkit.
Now, these aren't the
only topics in this unit,
but these are the bulk of it.
And to show you how
fundamental these ideas are,
I actually want to step
back just momentarily
outside of the realm of design for screens
and show you that the same
ideas are things you may have
unconsciously noticed in
totally different contexts.
So we'll return to UI
design in just a second,
but let's switch gears here
for just a couple minutes.
Say for a second that
you're out with friends,
and maybe someone you meet
invites you back to their place,
and you go back with a bunch of folks,
and you're all hanging out
in their stylish bachelor pad or whatever,
and it looks like this, all right.
This is a cool room.
Is it nicely designed?
Yeah, I would say it is.
Could you design a room like this?
Well, that's a different question.
Before I was a designer,
I would have said no way.
You know, there's some magic
behind how they lay things out
that I'm just not privy to.
I don't understand it.
It's above me.
But the truth is even if
you just pay attention
to a couple critical foundational ideas,
like alignment, white space, consistency,
you can actually figure out,
you can reverse engineer,
why this room looks nice,
and why it looks so elegant,
and we can start to apply
them to our own designs.
So take for instance alignment.
That's the first idea.
Maybe it's even the most important idea
that beginning designers miss.
If you look, there's a lot of alignment
going on in this room.
There's alignment, say, in
the little rug right here,
being aligned with the walls,
with all the furniture
being at right angles.
So this table is not twisted
around relative to the couch.
It's at right angles to the couch.
Same thing with these chairs.
Of these paintings on the wall,
all them are meticulously laid out
to be perfectly horizontal and vertical.
That's not unusual for
paintings on the wall.
I'm just saying the
more things in this room
that are aligned whether to
other elements in the room,
or just in the general sense
of there being parallel lines
suggested by multiple
elements in the room,
all of that stuff just
makes the room feel clean,
and sort of the design
field crisp and neat.
Now, whenever we have an idea
about what makes design work,
let's always test it by breaking it,
and let's say, hey, wait a second,
what happens if I look at, say,
something that's much messier, right?
There's no alignment here.
This is sort of the
antithesis of something
being well-aligned, and sure enough,
it doesn't look as nice.
Now, this is not exactly a
value judgment here, right?
This person who's working at this desk,
they're putting all their
attention into the work
on the screen, and not the surroundings.
But if you wanna make
something look presented,
then alignment is a great way to do it.
Alignment is sort of this signal that
a human being has put care into it,
and I do mean this quite literally.
If you look at nature,
nature is beautiful,
but it's never beautiful
because of alignment.
It's beautiful because of its grandness,
and because of its texture, and you know,
a whole bunch of other
reasons that are frankly
kind of outside the scope of this course.
But if you look at human-created things,
oftentimes they are beautiful
because of alignment,
or they look neat and crisp
and clean and designed
because of the alignment present.
Just look at how much alignment is here,
and there's a whole lesson
on this, by the way.
It's not like we just
need to cover it here.
We're gonna be talking for
30, 40 minutes about it.
But look how much alignment is suggested
by the edges of these cards all aligning,
and even the text within the
cards aligning vertically
and aligning horizontally
across the screen.
On this sidebar, yeah, you know,
this particular side
nav may not be aligned
with the headline or
any other element here,
but even within this
little area right here
all these icons are neatly centered.
Their center lines are aligned.
All this text is aligned by
its left edge, et cetera.
So there's just so much alignment.
It's really the default,
and if you want to make
something look carefully crafted,
then alignment matters.
You are going to be thinking
an enormous amount about it.
Let's go back to our bachelor pad here.
Another thing that makes
this look really nice
is the white space.
I say white space, spacing.
I use those terms interchangeably.
The thing is white space
doesn't have to be white.
One of the prime examples of
white space in this picture
right here is the fireplace.
The fireplace is the sole
element on this much larger wall,
and the fact that there's
all this space around it,
it's not blank.
In fact, it's textured, which
makes it look interesting.
But it also has these kind of mild,
somewhat visible lines of alignment
that also just kind of
add to that overall sense
of alignment of the entire room.
But it's the space around the fireplace
that makes it look like a focal point
and makes it look presented.
Likewise, you could even look
at this little table right here.
It's not exactly a big table,
but you could fit more than
these two things on it, right?
Or three, if that plant is right there.
It's a bit tough to see.
But the fact that this table
is not packed with stuff,
instead there's this one
book that says Paris on it,
and then there's some flowers,
and this thing, whatever this thing is,
it makes those three
things look presented.
It makes them look kind of elegant,
and just like alignment,
there's sort of a deeper lesson here.
When we look at something
designed by humans,
and we're presented only
with a small number of things
that are displayed with a
lot of space around them,
maybe it's the pictures on
the wall, or the fireplace,
or the few things on an
otherwise clean surface,
when we're presented just
with those few things,
we intuitively grasp that
we're meant to see those.
All of the unnecessary stuff,
all of the lesser stuff
is hidden from our view,
and we're just shown exactly
what we need, and just that.
Generous spacing will make
something feel simple,
elegant, and presented.
Now, again, let's look
at a counterexample.
Here's a image that I dug up,
and it's from a vendor's
stall in a marketplace,
and you can see there
are many things here,
but there is not much white space.
There's not much spacing.
And consequently, no one of these items
feels particularly presented.
Now there's other benefits.
There's a reason why this man
has laid out his shop this way.
But the idea of presenting
each item carefully,
and making everything
seem very considered,
and there for a very particular reason,
well, this doesn't do a great job at that.
Contrast that to something
like this gallery.
This gallery is really the
opposite end of the spectrum
because it's 99% white space.
The focal points of the room are actually
very few and far between.
And so, this feels more presented.
It feels more elegant.
It feels like more care
was put into figuring out
exactly what went here.
Now, again, this is not
a value judgment per se.
I'd actually much rather talk
to the proprietor of this shop
than whoever curated these photos.
But our goal here is to make things look
presented generally, to make them look
thoughtfully considered,
and often to avoid
having things feel cluttered or busy.
It's not to say there's never
a reason to have clutter
in your UI, but 99% of the
time, we're gonna be drawing
more lessons from this latter image.
Another fundamental
design we're gonna talk
a ton about is consistency.
Consistency is sort of the idea
that if things look similar
they belong together in a group.
And now, there's other ways
to say stuff belongs together
in a group, but consistency is
really, really good at that.
So for instance, look at, there's this,
you can't really see it,
but there's this three by
three grid of something
on the wall, photos, or paintings,
and you can tell that
because they all have
exactly the same frame
they belong together.
It would be kind of weird
if there were three of them
right here, and three of them
in a totally different spot
of the wall, maybe laid out vertically,
and three of them on this wall.
Hmm, nah, it wouldn't work.
Having that grid right
there where it's all clear
that these things belong together,
they look exactly the same,
that is a very strong signal.
Likewise, look at these two chairs.
They're exactly the same chair.
You don't need to own two
of exactly the same chair in your house.
There's no requirement for it,
but by putting two
chairs that are the same
next to each other, it's a
little bit easier on the eyes.
It's one less thing to take in.
It adds to the elements in the room,
but only minimally adds to the
visual clutter of the room.
And like I said, there's
other ways to show
that things belong together.
Probably the other
biggest one is in spacing
to put things that are
similar near each other,
and very often that
pairs with consistency.
These images are near each other.
These chairs are like six inches apart.
If you want to remove visual clutter,
take a bunch of elements,
make them look as consistent
as possible, and then
align them up in a row.
Now, I just wanna take one moment
and talk about a few
things from this photo
that actually we aren't even
covering in this unit per se,
but will come up later,
and the first is color.
You might notice that basically
everything in this room
except the wooden floor and
this plant here is gray.
And when I say gray in this course,
I always, unless I otherwise specify,
I'm always gonna be talking about
inclusive of white and black.
But if it's a white, a black, or a gray,
it's gray, it's grayscale,
and one of the things
that's really foundational
to the color unit and this course
and the whole system I
have for color is that
gray is the most important color.
It's really underutilized
by beginning designers,
and the reason it's great
is because it doesn't
unduly draw your attention.
It feels understated
and sort of minimalist.
On a related note, I will
also talk in the color unit
about gray being the most elegant color,
and likewise, you could imagine
that if you took everything
in this room that was
grayscale, and made it red,
and I'm not actually gonna
do that, unfortunately,
but you can imagine
this room would not have
the same sort of effect.
It would not as elegant,
would not feel as classy.
It would not feel as simple.
One other topic that I'm
not gonna talk a ton about,
but I will talk a little
bit about, is UX in general,
user experience, and people
mean different things
by these terms, but typically
I'm gonna talk about
UX to mean solving the user's problem,
and creating a solution
that's highly usable.
UX and UI are both very related.
They're really two sides of the same coin.
On one hand, you want to
solve the user's problem,
and you want to solve it well.
You wanna make a solution
that they can use
that's very intuitive and simple.
And on the other hand, you
also want that solution
to look nice and evoke the brand
that you are trying to evoke.
UX and UI interact in all
sorts of interesting ways.
Even if we claim to be focusing
almost purely on aesthetics,
still the usability of things matters,
and oftentimes it matters
by placing constraints
on exactly what our solutions look like.
So for instance, in the
usability of this room,
one thing is this couch and
these chairs and this table
are all kind of pushed
against this wall right here.
And you could imagine
that if they were closer
to the fireplace there could be certain,
quote, unquote, "usability
issues" with the room.
For instance, to walk to this next room,
if I'm standing right here,
if I'd just come down these steps,
I might have to walk all the
way around this furniture,
so I go 10 feet here, turn, turn again,
and then, you know, to avoid this wall,
and then and only then
can I go to this room.
And instead being able to
walk down these stairs,
and then go directly through to this room,
or to the balcony, or whatever it is,
is a much more usable layout.
It requires less work on the user's part
to navigate from A to B.
Now, would this room look as
nice if this stuff was shifted
a little bit more towards the fireplace?
Yeah, it probably wouldn't change
the aesthetics terribly much.
But the fact that human
beings need to use this room
sort of puts a constraint on
the overall set of solutions
that we can choose from.
Once we've figured out a
usable way to lay out the room,
then we look for a way to add alignment,
to add consistency, to
add generous white space,
to make the room look as good as possible,
given the constraints that we have.
Software is very similar,
and I actually have a
totally separate course
just on UX and usability.
This course is focused on
the visual side of design,
but I practice both.
They are very much two
sides of the same coin,
and it will come up plenty
throughout Learn UI Design,
small little UX concerns
inherent in how you space things,
or make things consistent.
Now, one thing that ties
together all the elements
of a UI design is the brand.
Everything sort of backs up
and evokes a particular brand.
The brand of this house
to me feels very elegant,
modern, luxurious, clean, simple.
Those are all adjectives that we might use
to describe the brand of a website.
But just because the
brand of an app design
or an interior design
changes doesn't mean that
the fundamentals change.
Here's something that's
slightly different.
It still looks very designed.
And so, in some sense it is similar,
but if you look at it, you'll
notice it's much warmer.
It's much cozier.
It doesn't feel quite so
pretentious, or urban.
This is no log cabin, but
it is a couple steps closer.
And if we look at this, we can still see
so many of those design
principles being followed.
We can see the alignment,
at least in how this rug is laid out,
the TV against the wall.
Interesting similarity here,
some white space around the
TV that is also textured,
but the texture has
these little horizontal
lines of alignment.
The couch, which is little
bit out of the photo here,
is also aligned to the
walls and to the rug.
We could see white space use to present
this golden art contraption
thing on the walls,
maybe even to some degree,
these items right here.
One thing that is pretty cool
about this photo, though,
is if you look one of the
things that makes it feel
much warmer and cozier is the fact that
there's so many warmer,
cozy colors and textures.
This rug, this wood here, of course,
there's more wood on the wall,
these Barcelona chairs are kind of brown.
There's this golden brown
thing on the wall right here,
and actually this is one of the key ideas
from the color unit is that
one of the easiest ways
to add color is to have
variations of the same color.
So these are all kind of variations
of a yellow, gold, brown set of hues.
And while I wouldn't
recommend using necessarily
these exact same colors in
a mobile app or a website,
the same general principle applies.
But enough about interior design.
Let's actually switch over,
and look at websites here.
So here's a design by Jan Losert.
This is a travel app called Placeist,
and I think this is a concept.
It's not actually a real app
to the best of my knowledge.
But if you take those
same principles that made
an interior design look great
in a context completely different
than designing a website,
you can actually still see them here.
For instance, just starting at the top,
look at the consistency between
these shapes right here.
First of all, three of them
are circles with icons in them.
They're the exact same size,
the exact same color,
the exact same layout.
Even this, while I assume
it's sort of an app icon,
is roughly the same size and
placement, alignment-wise,
that it feels like it
kind of almost blends in,
and it's only the color,
and the fact that it doesn't
have a little circle around it
that those strategic inconsistencies
that make us notice it.
Likewise, consistency between
these two buttons here.
I'm assuming the user has
already clicked this heart,
but before they did, it would have had,
it would have been a white
heart with a white outline
in the same style as this right here.
And all the similarities,
all the consistencies,
and how they're laid out with
the circle around the button,
and then the little numbers saying perhaps
the number of people
who have hearted this,
or added it to their map, or whatever,
all of these consistencies say, hey,
these two things are similar.
These are two buttons.
You can press either.
Either is just gonna tick
up this little number here,
and these are some of the actions
that you can take on this page.
There's consistency in these
three sharing method buttons.
There's consistency in the
four images of your friends
who have also liked this place.
There's consistencies between,
I guess this is the daytime temperature
and the nighttime temperature,
or maybe the high and the low.
It just seems like there's
very few things on this page
that are not repeated
basically identically
in a very consistent way.
Likewise, everything is
incredibly well-aligned.
The left side of the page, highly aligned,
the right side of the
page, except for the stuff
in the header, which kind of
sticks to the very outside
of the screen, it seems like
there's this content column,
which everything is very well-aligned to.
There's horizontal alignment
implied by these three labels,
which are also styled consistently.
Down below, this location label,
consistent with the other labels,
left aligned with the
label above it, et cetera.
And there's plenty of white space too.
It's not like there's
nothing on this page,
but there is, say, 40, 50 pixels,
generous spacing between
these different widgets here,
and kind of all throughout the page.
One little note about the color is,
and stay with me for a second here,
this page is almost all
grayscale, except for the imagery.
It's almost all grayscale.
The images just draw your eye so much,
and they're fantastic, so
that seems like a good thing.
They add to the sense of
design-ness of this page.
But everything else, the text
is gray, this map is gray,
these icons are gray, these
icons up here are gray,
this text is white, everything else,
except these beautiful images
of this beautiful location, is gray.
Oh, of course there are two exceptions,
and it is the active I
hearted this location,
and the little logo thing at the top.
And notice that both of
those exceptions are orange.
So defaulting to grayscale
and beautiful imagery
with just a little pop of
color in about that same hue.
These two oranges look like
they may actually be identical,
but I'm not sure.
So that's one app.
We can look at one more, a mobile one.
It does, coincidentally happens
to do with real estate here,
but those same principles
in this very different app still apply.
Everything very neatly aligned
vertically on the sides,
horizontally, these
three things are aligned.
We can look at these
little label value elements
all neatly aligned to the left side here
to the right side here,
horizontally for each row.
It's tough to find a single
element that is not aligned
with something else.
Likewise, there's plenty of white space.
Again, for a mobile app where
you need to display data,
it's not like you're gonna
have hundreds of pixels
of blank space, but
there's generous spacing,
so that nothing feels very crowded.
And there's also a lot of
interesting uses of consistency.
Notice that basically all the
buttons look exactly the same.
They're all in these little circles
hovering over the images.
There's one here, here, here, here, here.
These nav icons down here
aren't encircled per se,
but even the bar that they're
in is rounded at the sides,
and actually that idea
of circles around this,
there's consistency in that.
Look at these images, rounded.
Look at these cards, rounded.
Look at the border around the rent button.
I'm not sure why there
is a border around it,
why it's in its own little button here,
but that's rounded too.
Likewise, the pagination
through the images,
the fundamentals are all there.
And of course the color
just happens to also have
very few pops of color, largely grayscale,
a little bit of purple,
all from the same hue.
Hue at 263, hue at 260,
it's basically the same.
So when I say I wanna teach
you the practical fundamentals
of UI design, I'm serious.
These things are everywhere.
All right, so have I convinced you yet?
Making something look nice is not random.
There's a very specific
way that you can do it
using alignment, using
spacing, and consistency.
And this is not to say, by the way,
that design is not open-ended.
Design still is open-ended.
If you gave 100 great
designers a design challenge,
you would generate 100 solutions,
but you would be very surprised
at the similarities
between those solutions,
maybe not in the things like the colors
and the fonts they use,
although I think there
would be similarities there,
but even in things like
the way they use alignment,
the way they use spacing.
You will see these all over the place
and you will be using them
more than almost any other
single idea from this course.
So with that being said,
let's get started with them.